<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- References are listed here so that they can be called via Entity attributes later -->
<!ENTITY RFC1034 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1034.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC1035 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1035.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4033 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4033.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4034 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4034.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4035 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4035.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4398 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4398.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4509 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4509.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5155 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5155.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5914 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5914.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6781 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6781.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- PROCESSING INSTRUCTIONS - GENERAL -->
<!-- EACH ONE STARTS WITH '?' BELOW -->
<!-- give errors on I-D nits and perform DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc strict='yes' ?>
<?rfc toc='yes'?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<?rfc tocdepth='4'?>
<!-- END GENERAL PROCESSING -->
<!-- PROCESSING INSTRUCTIONS - CONTROL OF REFERENCES -->
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc symrefs='yes'?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space -->
<?rfc sortrefs='yes' ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc compact='yes' ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<?rfc subcompact='no' ?>
<!-- END REFERENCE PROCESSING -->
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-ietf-dnsop-negative-trust-anchors-10"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
     ipr values: full3978, noModification3978, noDerivatives3978
     you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN" 
     they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

  <!-- FRONT SECTION -->

  <front>
    <title abbrev="DNSSEC Negative Trust Anchors">Definition and Use of DNSSEC
    Negative Trust Anchors</title>

    <!-- add role='editor' attribute to author tag below for the editors if appropriate -->

    <author fullname="Paul Ebersman" initials="P." surname="Ebersman">
      <organization abbrev="Comcast">Comcast</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>One Comcast Center</street>

          <street>1701 John F. Kennedy Boulevard</street>

          <city>Philadelphia</city>

          <region>PA</region>

          <code>19103</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <email>ebersman-ietf@dragon.net</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>

      <!-- author role='editor' is an optional value here-->
    </author>

    <author fullname="Chris Griffiths" initials="C." surname="Griffiths">
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
        </postal>

        <email>cgriffiths@gmail.com</email>
      </address>

      <!-- author role='editor' is an optional value here -->
    </author>

    <author fullname="Warren Kumari" initials="W." surname="Kumari">
      <organization abbrev="Google">Google</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1600 Amphitheatre Parkway</street>

          <city>Mountain View</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>94043</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <email>warren@kumari.net</email>

        <uri>http://www.google.com</uri>
      </address>

      <!-- author role='editor' is an optional value here -->
    </author>

    <author fullname="Jason Livingood" initials="J." surname="Livingood">
      <organization abbrev="Comcast">Comcast</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>One Comcast Center</street>

          <street>1701 John F. Kennedy Boulevard</street>

          <city>Philadelphia</city>

          <region>PA</region>

          <code>19103</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <email>jason_livingood@cable.comcast.com</email>

        <uri>http://www.comcast.com</uri>
      </address>

      <!-- author role='editor' is an optional value here -->
    </author>

    <author fullname="Ralf Weber" initials="R." surname="Weber">
      <organization abbrev="Nominum">Nominum</organization>

      <address>
        <email>Ralf.Weber@nominum.com</email>

        <uri>http://www.nominum.com</uri>
      </address>

      <!-- author role='editor' is an optional value here -->
    </author>

    <date day="12" month="May" year="2015"/>

    <!-- META-DATA DECLARATIONS -->

    <area>Operations and Management Area</area>

    <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc; 'Internet Engineering Task Force' is fine for individual submissions.  -->

    <workgroup>Domain Name System Operations</workgroup>

    <!-- Keywords will be incorporated into HTML output files in a meta tag but they have no effect on text or nroff output. If you submit your draft to the RFC Editor, the keywords will be used for the search engine. -->

    <keyword>RFC</keyword>

    <keyword>Request for Comments</keyword>

    <keyword>I-D</keyword>

    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>

    <keyword>ISP</keyword>

    <keyword>Internet Service Provider</keyword>

    <keyword>DNS</keyword>

    <keyword>DNSSEC</keyword>

    <keyword>Negative Trust Anchors</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>DNS Security Extensions (DNSSEC) is now entering widespread
      deployment. However, domain signing tools and processes are not yet as
      mature and reliable as those for non-DNSSEC-related domain
      administration tools and processes. Negative Trust Anchors (described in
      this document) can be used to mitigate DNSSEC validation failures.</t>

      <t>[RFC Editor: Please remove this before publication. This document is
      being stored in github at
      https://github.com/wkumari/draft-livingood-dnsop-negative-trust-anchors
      . Authors accept pull requests, and keep the latest (edit buffer)
      versions there, so commenters can follow along at home.]</t>
    </abstract>

    <!-- END META-DATA DECLARATIONS -->
  </front>

  <!-- END FRONT SECTION -->

  <!-- MIDDLE SECTION -->

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction and motivation" toc="include">
      <t>This document defines a Negative Trust Anchor, which can be used
      during the transition to ubiquitous DNSSEC deployment. Negative Trust
      Anchors (NTAs) are configured locally on a validating DNS recursive
      resolver to shield end users from DNSSEC-related authoritative name
      server operational errors. Negative Trust Anchors are intended to be
      temporary, and should not be distributed by IANA or any other
      organization outside of the administrative boundary of the organization
      locally implementing a Negative Trust Anchor. Finally, Negative Trust
      Anchors pertain only to DNSSEC and not to Public Key Infrastructures
      (PKI) such as X.509.</t>

      <t>DNSSEC has now entered widespread deployment. However, the DNSSEC
      signing tools and processes are less mature and reliable than those for
      non-DNSSEC-related administration. As a result, operators of DNS
      recursive resolvers, such as Internet Service Providers (ISPs),
      occasionally observe domains incorrectly managing DNSSEC-related
      resource records. This mismanagement triggers DNSSEC validation
      failures, and then causes large numbers of end users to be unable to
      reach a domain. Many end users tend to interpret this as a failure of
      their ISP or resolver operator, and may switch to a non-validating
      resolver or contact their ISP to complain, rather than seeing this as a
      failure on the part of the domain they wanted to reach. Without the
      techniques in this document, this pressure may cause the resolver
      operator to disable (or simply not deploy) DNSSEC validation. Use of a
      Negative Trust Anchor to temporarily disable DNSSEC validation for a
      specific misconfigured domain name immediately restores access for end
      users. This allows the domain's administrators to fix their
      misconfiguration, while also allowing the organization using the
      Negative Trust Anchor to keep DNSSEC validation enabled and still reach
      the misconfigured domain.</t>

      <t>It is worth noting the following text from <xref target="RFC4033"/> -
      "In the final analysis, however, authenticating both DNS keys and data
      is a matter of local policy, which may extend or even override the
      protocol extensions defined in this document set." A responsibility (one
      of many) of a caching server operator is to "protect the integrity of
      the cache."</t>

      <section anchor="Definition-of-a-Negative-Trust-Anchor"
               title="Definition of a Negative Trust Anchor" toc="include">
        <t>Trust Anchors are defined in <xref target="RFC5914"/>. A trust
        anchor should be used by a validating caching resolver as a starting
        point for building the authentication chain for a signed DNS response.
        By way of analogy, negative trust anchors stop validation of the
        authentication chain. Instead, the validator treats any upstream
        responses as if the zone is unsigned and does not set the AD bit in
        responses it sends to clients. Note that this is a behavior, and not a
        separate resource record. This Negative Trust Anchor can potentially
        be implemented at any level within the chain of trust and would stop
        validation from that point in the chain down. Validation starts again
        if there is a positive trust anchor further down in the chain. For
        example, if there is a NTA at example.com, and a positive trust anchor
        at foo.bar.example.com, then validation resumes for
        foo.bar.example.com and anything below it.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="Domain-Validation-Failures"
               title="Domain Validation Failures" toc="include">
        <t>A domain name can fail validation for two general reasons: a
        legitimate security failure such as due to an attack or compromise of
        some sort, or as a result of misconfiguration on the part of an domain
        administrator. As domains transition to DNSSEC, the most common reason
        for a validation failure has been misconfiguration. Thus, domain
        administrators should be sure to read <xref target="RFC6781"/> in
        full. They should also pay special attention to Section 4.2,
        pertaining to key rollovers, which appear to be the cause of many
        recent validation failures.</t>

        <t>It is also possible that some DNSSEC validation failures could
        arise due to differences in how different software developers
        interpret DNSSEC standards and/or how those developers choose to
        implement support for DNSSEC. For example, it is conceivable that a
        domain may be DNSSEC signed properly, and one vendor's DNS recursive
        resolvers will validate the domain but other vendors' software may
        fail to validate the domain.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="End-User-Reaction" title="End User Reaction"
               toc="include">
        <t>End users generally do not know of, understand, or care about the
        resolution process that causes connections to happen. This is by
        design: the point of the DNS is to insulate users from having to
        remember IP addresses through a friendlier way of naming systems. It
        follows from this that end users do not, and should not, be expected
        to know about DNSSEC, validation, or anything of the sort. As a
        result, end users may misinterpret the failure to reach a domain due
        to DNSSEC-related misconfiguration . They may (incorrectly) assume
        that their ISP is purposely blocking access to the domain or that it
        is a performance failure on the part of their ISP (especially of the
        ISP's DNS servers). They may contact their ISP to complain, which will
        incur cost for their ISP. In addition, they may use online tools and
        sites to complain of this problem, such as via a blog, web forum, or
        social media site, which may lead to dissatisfaction on the part of
        other end users or general criticism of an ISP or operator of a DNS
        recursive resolver.</t>

        <t>As end users publicize these failures, others may recommend they
        switch from security-aware DNS resolvers to resolvers not performing
        DNSSEC validation. This is a shame since the ISP or other DNS
        recursive resolver operator is actually doing exactly what they are
        supposed to do in failing to resolve a domain name; this is the
        expected result when a domain can no longer be validated and it
        protects end users from a potential security threat. Use of a Negative
        Trust Anchor would allow the ISP to specifically remedy the failure to
        reach that domain, without compromising security for other sites. This
        would result in a satisfied end user, with minimal impact to the ISP,
        while maintaining the security of DNSSEC for correctly maintained
        domains.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="Switching-to-a-Non-Validating-Resolver-is-Not-Recommended"
               title="Switching to a Non-Validating Resolver is Not Recommended"
               toc="include">
        <t>As noted in <xref target="End-User-Reaction"/>, some people may
        consider switching to an alternative, non-validating resolver
        themselves, or may recommend that others do so. But if a domain fails
        DNSSEC validation and is inaccessible, this could very well be due to
        a security-related issue. In order to be as safe and secure as
        possible, end users should not change to DNS servers that do not
        perform DNSSEC validation as a workaround, and people should not
        recommend that others do so either. Domains that fail DNSSEC for
        legitimate reasons (versus misconfiguration) may be in control of
        hackers or there could be other significant security issues with the
        domain.</t>

        <t>Thus, switching to a non-validating resolver to restore access to a
        domain that fails DNSSEC validation is not a recommended practice, is
        bad advice to others, is potentially harmful to end user security.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Use-of-a-Negative-Trust-Anchor"
             title="Use of a Negative Trust Anchor" toc="include">
      <t>Technical personnel trained in the operation of DNS servers MUST
      confirm that a failure is due to misconfiguration, as a similar breakage
      could have occurred if an attacker gained access to a domain's
      authoritative servers and modified those records or had the domain
      pointed to their own rogue authoritative servers. They should also
      confirm that the domain is not intentionally broken, such as for testing
      purposes as noted in <xref target="Intentionally-Broken-Domains"/>.
      Finally, they should make a reasonable attempt to contact the domain
      owner of the misconfigured zone, preferably prior to implementing the
      Negative Trust Anchor. Involving trained technical personnel is costly,
      but operational experience suggests that this is a very rare event,
      usually on the order of once per quarter (or even less).</t>

      <t>It is important for the resolver operator to confirm that the domain
      is still under the ownership / control of the legitimate owner of the
      domain in order to ensure that disabling validation for a specific
      domain does not direct users to an address under an attacker's control.
      Contacting the domain owner and telling them the DNSSEC records that the
      resolver operator is seeing allows the resolver operator to determine if
      the issue is a DNSSEC misconfiguration or an attack.</t>

      <t>In the case of a validation failure due to misconfiguration of a TLD
      or popular domain name (such as a top 100 website), content or services
      in the affected TLD or domain could be inaccessible for a large number
      of users. In such cases, it may be appropriate to use a Negative Trust
      Anchor as soon as the misconfiguration is confirmed. An example of a
      list of "top N" websites is the <xref target="Alexa">"Alexa Top 500
      Sites on the Web" </xref>, , or a list of the of the most-accessed names
      in the resolver's cache.</t>

      <t>Once a domain has been confirmed to fail DNSSEC validation due to a
      DNSSEC-related misconfiguration, an ISP or other DNS recursive resolver
      operator may elect to use a Negative Trust Anchor for that domain or
      sub-domain. This instructs their DNS recursive resolver to temporarily
      NOT perform DNSSEC validation at or in the misconfigured domain. This
      immediately restores access to the domain for end users while the
      domain's administrator corrects the misconfiguration(s). It does not and
      should not involve turning off validation more broadly.</t>

      <t>A Negative Trust Anchor MUST only be used for a limited duration.
      Implementors SHOULD allow the operator using the Negative Trust Anchor
      to set an end time and date associated with any Negative Trust Anchor.
      Optimally, this time and date is set in a DNS recursive resolver's
      configuration, though in the short-term this may also be achieved via
      other systems or supporting processes. Use of a Negative Trust Anchor
      MUST NOT be automatic.</t>

      <t>Finally, a Negative Trust Anchor SHOULD be used only in a specific
      domain or sub-domain and MUST NOT affect validation of other names up
      the authentication chain. For example, a Negative Trust Anchor for
      zone1.example.com would affect only names at or below zone1.example.com,
      and validation would still be performed on example.com, .com, and the
      root ("."). This Negative Trust Anchor also SHOULD NOT affect names in
      another branch of the tree (such as example.net). In another example, a
      Negative Trust Anchor for example.com would affect only names within
      example.com, and validation would still be performed on .com, and the
      root ("."). In this scenario, if there is a (probably manually
      configured) trust anchor for zone1.example.com, validation would be
      performed for zone1.example.com and subdomains of zone1.example.com.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Managing-Negative-Trust-Anchors"
             title="Managing Negative Trust Anchors" toc="include">
      <t>While Negative Trust Anchors have proven useful during the early
      stages of DNSSEC adoption, domain owners are ultimately responsible for
      managing and ensuring their DNS records are configured correctly.</t>

      <t>Most current implementations of DNS validating resolvers currently
      follow <xref target="RFC4033"/> on configuring a Trust Anchor using
      either a public key as in a DNSKEY RR or a hash of a public key as in a
      DS RR.</t>

      <t>Different DNS validators may have different configuration names for a
      Negative Trust Anchor. For examples see Appendix A.</t>

      <t>An NTA placed at a node where there is a configured positive trust
      anchor MUST take precedence over that trust anchor, effectively
      disabling it. Implementations MAY issue a warning or informational
      message when this occurs, so that operators are not surprised when this
      happens.</t>

      <section title="Alerting Users to NTA Use">
        <t>End users of a DNS recursive resolver or other people may wonder
        why a domain that fails DNSSEC validation resolves with a supposedly
        validating resolver. As a result, implementors should consider
        transparently disclosing those Negative Trust Anchors which are
        currently in place or were in place in the past, such as on a website
        <xref target="Disclosure-Example"/>.</t>

        <t>This is particularly important since there is currently no special
        DNS query response code that could indicate to end users or
        applications that a Negative Trust Anchor is in place. Such
        disclosures should optimally include both the data and time that the
        Negative Trust Anchor was put in place and when it was removed.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Removal-of-a-Negative-Trust-Anchor"
             title="Removal of a Negative Trust Anchor" toc="include">
      <t>As explored in <xref target="Security-Considerations"/>, using an NTA
      once the zone correctly validates can have security considerations. It
      is therefore RECOMMENDED that NTA implementors SHOULD periodically
      attempt to validate the domain in question, for the period of time that
      the Negative Trust Anchor is in place, until such validation is again
      successful. NTAs MUST expire automatically when their configured
      lifetime ends. The lifetime MUST NOT exceed a week. Before removing the
      Negative Trust Anchor, all authoritative resolvers listed in the zone
      should be checked (due to anycast and load balancers it may not be
      possible to check all instances).</t>

      <t>Once all testing succeeds, a Negative Trust Anchor should be removed
      as soon as is reasonably possible. One possible method to automatically
      determine when the NTA can be removed is to send a periodic query for
      type SOA at the NTA node; if it gets a response that it can validate
      (whether the response was an actual SOA answer or a NOERROR/NODATA with
      appropriate NSEC/NSEC3 records), the NTA is presumed no longer to be
      necessary and is removed. Implementations SHOULD, by default, perform
      this operation. Note that under some circumstances this is undesirable
      behavior (for example, if www.example.com has a bad signature, but
      example.com/SOA is fine) and so implementations may wish to allow the
      operator to override this spot-check / behavior.</t>

      <t>When removing the NTA, the implementation SHOULD remove all cached
      entries at and below the NTA node.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Comparison-to-Other-DNS-Misconfigurations"
             title="Comparison to Other DNS Misconfigurations" toc="include">
      <t>Domain administrators are ultimately responsible for managing and
      ensuring their DNS records are configured correctly. ISPs or other DNS
      recursive resolver operators cannot and should not correct misconfigured
      A, CNAME, MX, or other resource records of domains for which they are
      not authoritative. Expecting non-authoritative entities to protect
      domain administrators from any misconfiguration of resource records is
      therefore unrealistic and unreasonable, and in the long-term is harmful
      to the delegated design of the DNS and could lead to extensive
      operational instability and/or variation.</t>

      <t>With DNSSEC breakage, it is often possible to tell that there is a
      misconfiguration by looking at the data and not needing to guess what it
      should have been.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Intentionally-Broken-Domains"
             title="Intentionally Broken Domains" toc="include">
      <t>Some domains, such as dnssec-failed.org, have been intentionally
      broken for testing purposes <xref
      target="Measuring-DNSSEC-Validation-of-Website-Visitors"/> <xref
      target="Netalyzr"/>. For example, dnssec-failed.org is a DNSSEC-signed
      domain that is broken. If an end user is querying a validating DNS
      recursive resolver, then this or other similarly intentionally broken
      domains should fail to resolve and should result in a "Server Failure"
      error (RCODE 2, also known as 'SERVFAIL'). If such a domain resolved
      successfully, then it is a sign that the DNS recursive resolver is not
      fully validating.</t>

      <t>Organizations that utilize Negative Trust Anchors should not add a
      Negative Trust Anchor for any intentionally broken domain. Such
      additions are prevented by the requirement that the operator attempt to
      contact the administrators for the zone that has broken DNSSEC.</t>

      <t>Organizations operating an intentionally broken domain may wish to
      consider adding a TXT record for the domain to the effect of "This
      domain is purposely DNSSEC broken for testing purposes".</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Discovering broken domains">
      <t>Discovering that a domain is DNSSEC broken as result of an operator
      error instead of an attack is not trivial, and the examples here should
      be vetted by an experienced professional before taking the decision on
      implementing an negative trust anchor.</t>

      <t>One of the key thing to look for when looking at a DNSSEC broken
      domain is consistency and history. It therefore is good if you have the
      ability to look at the server's DNS traffic over a long period of time
      or have a database that stores DNS names associated answers (this is
      often referred to as a "passive DNS database"). Another invaluable tool
      is dnsviz (http://www.dnsivz.net) which also stores DNSSEC related data
      historically. The drawback here is that you need to have it test the
      domain before the incident occurs.</t>

      <t>The first and easiest thing to check is if the failure of the domain
      is consistent across different software implementations. If not, you
      want to inform the vendor where it fails so that the vendor can look
      more deeply into the issue.</t>

      <t>The next thing is to figure out what the actual failure mode is.
      There are several tools to do this, an incomplete list includes:<list
          style="symbols">
          <t>DNSViz (http://dnsviz.net)</t>

          <t>Verisign DNSSEC debugger
          (http://dnssec-debugger.verisignlabs.com)</t>

          <t>iis.se DNS check (http://dnscheck.iis.se)</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>most of these tools are open source and can be installed locally.
      However, using the tools over the Internet has the advantage of
      providing visibility from a different point.</t>

      <t>Once you figure out what the error is, you need to check if it shows
      consistently around the world and from all authoritative servers. Use
      DNS Tools (dig) or DNS looking glasses to verify this. An error that is
      consistently the same is more likely to be operator caused than an
      attack. Also if the output from the authoritative server is consistently
      different from the resolvers output this hints to an attack rather then
      an error, unless there is EDNS0 client subnet
      (draft-ietf-dnsop-edns-client-subnet) applied to the domain.</t>

      <t>A last check is to look at the actual DNS data. Is the result of the
      query still the same or has it changed? While a lot of DNSSEC errors
      occur on events that change DNSSEC data, the actual record someone wants
      to go to often stays the same. If the data is the same, this is an
      indication (not a guarantee) that the error is operator caused. Keep in
      mind that with DNS being used to globally balance traffic the data
      associated to a name might be different in different parts of the
      Internet.</t>

      <t>Here are some examples of common DNSSEC failures that have been seen
      as operator signing errors on the Internet:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>RRSIG timing issue. Each signature has an inception time and
          expiry time, between which it is valid. Letting this time expire
          without creating a new signature is one of the most common DNSSEC
          errors. To a lesser extent, this also occurs if signatures were made
          active before the inception time. For all of these errors your
          primary check is to check on the data. Signature expiration is also
          about the only error we see on actual data (like www.example.com).
          All other errors are more or less related to dealing with the chain
          of trust established by DS records in the parent zone and DNSKEYs in
          the child zones. These mostly occur during key rollovers, but are
          not limited to that.</t>

          <t>DNSKEYs in child zone don't match the DS record in the parent
          zone. There is a big variation of this that can happen at any point
          in the key lifecycle. DNSViz is the best tools to show problems in
          the chain. If you debug yourself use dig +multiline so that you can
          see the key id of a DNSKEY. Common Variations of this can be:<list
              style="symbols">
              <t>DS pointing to a non existent key in the child zone.
              Questions for consideration here include: Has there ever been a
              key (and, if so, was it used)? Has there been a recent change in
              the DNSKEY RRSet (indicating a key rollover)? Has the actual
              data in the zone changed? Is the zone DNSSEC signed at all and
              has it been in the past?</t>

              <t>DS pointing to an existent key, but no signatures are made
              with the key. The checks above should be done, with the addition
              of checking if another key in the DNSKEY RRSet is now used to
              sign the records.</t>

              <t>Data in DS or DNSKEY doesn't match the other. This is more
              common in initial setup when there was a copy and paste error.
              Again checking history on data is the best you can do there.</t>
            </list></t>
        </list></t>

      <t>All of the above is just a starting point for consideration when
      deciding whether or not to deploy a trust anchor. It is not possible to
      provide a simple checklist to run through to determine whether a domain
      is broken because of an attack or an operator error.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Other-Considerations" title="Other Considerations"
             toc="include">
      <section anchor="Security-Considerations"
               title="Security Considerations" toc="include">
        <t>End to end DNSSEC validation will be disabled during the time that
        a Negative Trust Anchor is used. In addition, the Negative Trust
        Anchor may be in place after the point in time when the DNS
        misconfiguration that caused validation to break has been fixed. Thus,
        there may be a gap between when a domain has been re-secured and when
        a Negative Trust Anchor is removed. In addition, a Negative Trust
        Anchor may be put in place by DNS recursive resolver operators without
        the knowledge of the authoritative domain administrator for a given
        domain name. However, attempts SHOULD be made to contact and inform
        the domain administrator prior to putting the NTA in place.</t>

        <t>One side effect of implementing an NTA is that it may break client
        applications that assume that a domain is signed and expect an AD bit
        in the response. It is expected that many application that require
        DNSSEC for a domain will perform their own validation, and so this
        should not be a major issue.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="Privacy-Considerations" title="Privacy Considerations"
               toc="include">
        <t>There are no privacy considerations in this document.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="IANA-Considerations" title="IANA Considerations"
               toc="include">
        <t>There are no IANA considerations in this document.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements" toc="include">
      <t>Several people made contributions of text to this document and/or
      played an important role in the development and evolution of this
      document. This in some cases included performing a detailed review of
      this document and then providing feedback and constructive criticism for
      future revisions, or engaging in a healthy debate over the subject of
      the document. All of this was helpful and therefore the following
      individuals merit acknowledgement: Joe Abley, John Barnitz, Tom
      Creighton, Marco Davids, Brian Dickson, Patrik Falstrom, Tony Finch,
      Chris Ganster, Olafur Gudmundsson, Peter Hagopian, Wes Hardaker, Paul
      Hoffman, Shane Kerr, Murray Kucherawy, Rick Lamb, Marc Lampo, Scott
      Rose, Ted Lemon, A. Schulze, Antoin Verschuren, Paul Vixie, Patrik
      Wallstrom, W.C.A. Wijngaards, Nick Weaver</t>

      <t>Edward Lewis, Evan Hunt, Andrew Sullivan and Tatuya Jinmei provided
      especially large amounts of text and / or detailed review.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <!-- END MIDDLE SECTION -->

  <!-- BACK SECTION -->

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC4033;

      &RFC5914;

      &RFC6781;
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <reference anchor="Measuring-DNSSEC-Validation-of-Website-Visitors"
                 target="http://jpmens.net/2012/07/30/is-my-web-site-being-used-via-dnssec-validator/">
        <front>
          <title>Is my Web site being used via a DNSSEC-validator?</title>

          <author fullname="Jan-Piet Mens" initials="J.P." surname="Mens"/>

          <date day="30" month="July" year="2012"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Netalyzr"
                 target="http://conferences.npl.co.uk/satin/presentations/satin2011slides-Weaver.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>Implications of Netalyzr's DNS Measurements</title>

          <author fullname="Nicholas Weaver" initials="N." surname="Weaver">
            <organization abbrev="ICSI">ICSI</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Christian Kreibich" initials="C."
                  surname="Kreibich">
            <organization abbrev="ICSU">ICSI</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Boris Nechaev" initials="B." surname="Nechaev">
            <organization abbrev="HIIT/TKK">HIIT/TKK</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Vern Paxson" initials="V." surname="Paxson">
            <organization abbrev="ICSI-UC Berkeley">ICSI and UC
            Berkeley</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="5" month="April" year="2011"/>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Securing and Trusting Internet Names, SATIN 2011"
                    value="SATIN 2011"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Unbound-Configuration"
                 target="http://unbound.net/documentation/howto_turnoff_dnssec.html">
        <front>
          <title>Unbound: How to Turn Off DNSSEC</title>

          <author fullname="W.C.A. Wijngaards" initials="W.C.A."
                  surname="Wijngaards">
            <organization abbrev="NLnet">NLnet Labs</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="June" year="2010"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Disclosure-Example"
                 target="http://dns.comcast.net/index.php/entry/faa-gov-failing-dnssec-validation-fixed">
        <front>
          <title>faa.gov Failing DNSSEC Validation (Fixed)</title>

          <author>
            <organization abbrev="Comcast">Comcast</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="13" month="February" year="2013"/>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Comcast" value=""/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Alexa" target="http://www.alexa.com/topsites">
        <front>
          <title>Alexa "The top 500 sites on the web. "</title>

          <author fullname="Alexa">
            <organization abbrev="Comcast">Alexa, an Amazon.com
            Company</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="9" month="May" year="2015"/>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="" value=""/>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <section title="Configuration Examples">
      <t>The section contains example configurations to achieve Negative Trust
      Anchor functionality for the zone foo.example.com.</t>

      <t>Note: These are simply examples - nameserver operators are expected
      to test and understand the implications of these operations. Note also
      that some of available implementations may not implement all recommended
      functionality in this document. In that case it is advisable to request
      the developer or vendor of the implementation to support the missing
      feature, rather than start using the incomplete implementation.</t>

      <section title="NLNet Labs Unbound">
        <t>Unbound lets us simply disable validation checking for a specific
        zone by adding configuration statements to unbound.conf:</t>

        <t><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[server:
        domain-insecure: "foo.example.com"
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>Using the 'unbound-control' command one can add and remove Negative
        Trust Anchors without restarting the nameserver.</t>

        <t><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[   Using the "unbound-control" command:
        list_insecure                 list domain-insecure zones
        insecure_add zone             add domain-insecure zone
        insecure_remove zone          remove domain-insecure zone
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>Items added with the "unbound-control" command are added to the
        running server and are lost when the server is restarted. Items from
        unbound.conf stay after restart.</t>

        <t>For additional information see <xref
        target="Unbound-Configuration"/></t>
      </section>

      <section title="ISC BIND">
        <t>Use the "rndc" command:</t>

        <t><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[  nta -dump
            List all negative trust anchors.
  nta [-lifetime duration] [-force] domain [view]
            Set a negative trust anchor, disabling DNSSEC validation
            for the given domain.
            Using -lifetime specifies the duration of the NTA, up
            to one week. The default is one hour.
            Using -force prevents the NTA from expiring before its
            full lifetime, even if the domain can validate sooner.
  nta -remove domain [view]
            Remove a negative trust anchor, re-enabling validation
            for the given domain.]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Nominum Vantio">
        <t><spanx style="strong"/></t>

        <t><spanx style="strong">negative-trust-anchors</spanx></t>

        <t><spanx style="emph">Format</spanx>: name</t>

        <t><spanx style="emph">Command Channel</spanx>: view.update name=world
        negative-trust-anchors=(foo.example.com)</t>

        <t><spanx style="emph">Command Channel</spanx>: resolver.update
        name=res1 negative-trust-anchors=(foo.example.com)</t>

        <t><spanx style="strong">Description</spanx>: Disables DNSSEC
        validation for a domain, even if the domain is under an existing
        security root.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Document Change Log">
      <t>[RFC Editor: This section is to be removed before publication]</t>

      <t>-10 to 11<list style="symbols">
          <t>Incoroprated comments from IETF LC, including:</t>

          <t>A. Schulze - s/Unound/Unbound/</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>-10 to 10.1<list style="symbols">
          <t>Fixed some typos (e.g Anrew -&gt; Andrew)</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>-09 to -10<list style="symbols">
          <t>'Implementations MAY issue a warning or informational message
          when this occurs' - changed SHOULD to MAY, per Evan.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>-08 to -09<list style="symbols">
          <t>Clarified that an NTA MUST take precedence over a positive, local
          TA.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>-07 to -08<list style="symbols">
          <t>Added some cleanup from Paul Hoffman and Evan Hunt.</t>

          <t>Some better text on how to make Unbound do this, provided by
          W.C.A. Wijngaards.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>-06 to -07<list style="symbols">
          <t>Addressed a large number of comments from Paul Hoffman, Scott
          Rose and some more from Jinmei.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>-05 to -06</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>A bunch of comments from Tony Finch.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>-04 to -05</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>A large bunch of cleanups from Jinmei. Thanks!</t>

          <t>Also clarified that if there is an NTA at foo.bar.baz.example,
          and a positive *trust anchor* at bar.baz.example, the most specific
          wins. I'm not very happy with this text, any additional text
          gratefully accepted...</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>-03 to -04:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Addressed some comment from an email from Jinmei that I had
          missed. Turns out others had made many of the same comments, and so
          most had already been addressed.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>-02 to -03:<list style="symbols">
          <t>Included text from Ralph into Appendix B</t>

          <t>A bunch of comments from Andrew Sullivan ('[DNSOP]
          negative-trust-anchors-02" - Mar 18th)</t>

          <t>Updated keywords</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>-01 to -02:<list style="symbols">
          <t>Gah! I forgot to run spell check. And I type like a chimpanzee
          with bad hand-eye coordination...</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>-00 to -01:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Stole chunks of text from Ed Lewis' mailing list "tirade" :-)</t>

          <t>New rndc usage text from Evan.</t>

          <t>Deleted the (already resolved) open issues from Appendix C, moved
          the unresolved issues into github, resolved them!</t>

          <t>Clarification that automated removal is best removal method, and
          how to implement (Evan Hunt)</t>

          <t>Clarify that an NTA is not a RR (Rick Lamb)</t>

          <t>Grammar fixes.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Ind-07 - WG-00:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Simply updated name to reflect WG doc.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Individual-00: First version published as an individual draft.</t>

      <t>Individual-01: Fixed minor typos and grammatical nits. Closed all
      open editorial items.</t>

      <t>Individual-02: Simple date change to keep doc from expiring.
      Substantive updates planned.</t>

      <t>Individual-03: Changes to address feedback from Paul Vixie, by adding
      a new section "Limited Time and Scope of Use". Changes to address issues
      raised by Antoin Verschuren and Patrik Wallstrom, by adding a new
      section "Intentionally Broken Domains" and added two related references.
      Added text to address the need for manual investigation, as suggested by
      Patrik Falstrom. Added a suggestion on notification as suggested by Marc
      Lampo. Made several additions and changes suggested by Ralf Weber, Wes
      Hardaker, Nick Weaver, Tony Finch, Shane Kerr, Joe Abley, Murray
      Kucherawy, Olafur Gudmundsson.</t>

      <t>Individual-04: Moved the section defining a NTA forward, and added
      new text to the Abstract and Introduction per feedback from Paul
      Hoffman.</t>

      <t>Individual-05: Incorporated feedback from the DNSOP WG list received
      on 2/17/13 and 2/18/13. This is likely the final version before the IETF
      86 draft cutoff date. Updated references to RFC6781 to RFC6781, per
      March Davids.</t>

      <t>Individual-06: Added more OPEN issues to continue tracking WG
      discussion. No changes in the main document - just expanded issue
      tracking.</t>

      <t>Individual-07: Refresh document - needs revision and rework before
      IETF-91. Planning to add more contributors.</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Using github issue tracker - go see
          https://github.com/wkumari/draft-livingood-dnsop-negative-trust-anchors
          for more details.</t>

          <t>A bunch of readability improvments.</t>

          <t>Issue: Notify the domain owner of the validation failure -
          resolved.</t>

          <t>Issue: Make the NTA as specific as possible - resolved.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>
  </back>

  <!-- END BACK SECTION -->
</rfc>
<!-- FOR REFERENCE -->
<!-- less than is &lt -->
<!-- ampersand is &amp -->
<!-- apostrophe is &apos -->
<!-- quotation is &quot -->
